Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is קי"ג, Kuf Yud
Gimmel, 113, and we are in the last פרק Perek and we
are dealing and we've read the whole long משנה, Mishnah, which is
all the משניות Mishnayot of this last פרק, Perek, and now we're
going to start the גמרא. Gemara. And we're still right now in
the discussions of שחוטי חוץ Shchutei Chutz and the משנה Mishnah said
that if one שחט Shechts the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah out of
its גיתה, Gitta, literally its vat, its location, that's not a חיוב
Chiyuv of שחוטי חוץ Shchutei Chutz because the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
is not fit to go to אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, it's not
ראוי לאהל מועד. Ra'uy Le'ohel Moed. It's not ראוי Ra'uy to be
brought in the מקדש. Mikdash. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: מאי
חוץ מגיתה? Mai Chutz Migitta? What does that phrase mean, outside of
its gut, outside of its vat, outside of its location? What is
its location? I mean, it could be brought anywhere presumably anywhere outside
of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So אמר ריש לקיש: Amar Resh Lakish: חוץ ממקום
הבדוק לה. Chutz Mimakom Habaduk Lah. No, its location is places that
have been checked to make sure that there are no buried graves,
there are no little pieces of bone, that it's a place that
is definitely טהור. Tahor. And so if you take it outside of
that and you bring it to a place that is possibly טמא,
Tamei, that has not been checked and verified, then that is not
its location and nevertheless you're not חייב Chayav for שחוטי חוץ Shchutei
Chutz because it's not something that would be brought in the מקדש.
Mikdash. אמר לו רבי יוחנן: Amar Lo Rabbi Yochanan: So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan said back, וכל ארץ ישראל בדוקה היא? Vechol Eretz Yisrael
Bedukah Hi? What do you mean? The entire land of ישראל Yisrael
you can assume that any place that's not officially like marked as
a cemetery, you don't have to be concerned about that there might
be some dead bodies there, so it is actually every-
the meaning of חוץ מגיתה Chutz Migitta cannot be in a location
that is doubt, you know, that has not been checked because the
default is that all of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is טהור. Tahor.
That's quite interesting. As I said, obviously there are cemeteries, but those
are marked and they would go out of their way to like
mark places where they thought there might be a dead body and
so on. So he says we do not have to check spaces
that we are not aware of, at least מעיקר הדין. Me'ikar Hadin.
Okay, so if that's true, אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ela Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, so what does רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say it means outside
of its place? What place would not be acceptable for a פרה
אדומה? Parah Adumah? I suppose you could say you actually brought it
into a cemetery, but alright, that would be a little extreme. So
let's see what he says. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ela Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, כגון ששחטה לפנים מחומת ירושלים, Kegon Sheshachtah Lifnim Mechomat Yerushalayim,
that you have to actually שחט Shecht it outside of the camp,
the camp now being ירושלים Yerushalayim once they get to ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. That defines מחנה ישראל. Machaneh Yisrael. So if you שחט
Shecht it in the camp, that's not in its acceptable place. And
nevertheless you're not חייב Chayav for שחוטי חוץ. Shchutei Chutz. ונוקמה כגון
ששחטה חוץ לחומתו שלא
כנגד הפתח? Venokmah Kegon Sheshachtah Chutz Lechomato Shelo Keneged Hapetch?
One minute, it's very easy to find a place even outside ירושלים
Yerushalayim that is not considered to be the proper place of the
פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. And that is if you שחט Shecht it
in a place that is not directly to the east of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and is not facing the opening of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash because the תורה Torah certainly when it speaks
about the sprinkling of the blood says you shall sprinkle it towards
פתח אהל מועד. Petach Ohel Moed. Here's the פסוק. Pasuk. It says:
ונתתם אותה אל אלעזר הכהן והוציא אותה אל מחוץ למחנה, Unatatem Otah
El Elazar Hakohen Vehotzi Otah El Michutz Lamachaneh, outside the camp, that's
outside ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ושחט אותה
לפניו, Veshachat Otah Lefanav, and שחט, Shecht, ולקח אלעזר הכהן מדמה באצבעו
והזה אל נוכח פני אהל מועד מדמה שבע פעמים. Velakach Elazar Hakohen
Midamah Be'etzba'o Vehizah El Nochach Pnei Ohel Moed Midamah Sheva Pe'amim. Take
the blood and sprinkle towards אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So why not
just say it was שחט Shecht not facing אהל מועד? Ohel Moed?
ונוקמה שלא כנגד הפתח, Venokmah Shelo Keneged Hapetch, דאמר רב אדא בר
אהבה, De'amar Rav Adda Bar Ahava, שחטה שלא כנגד הפתח פסולה. Shechtah
Shelo Keneged Hapetch Psulah. If you שחט Shecht it not facing the
opening of the מקדש, Mikdash, not the direct east, it is invalid.
שנאמר ושחט והזה. Shene'emar Veshachat Vehizah. מה הזאה
כנגד פתח אף שחיטה כנגד פתח. Mah Haza'ah Keneged Petach Af Shechitah
Keneged Petach. Now, that's not explicit in the פסוק. Pasuk. What's explicit
in the פסוק Pasuk is the blood has to be sprinkled towards
the opening, sort of like somewhat of a quasi קרבן Korban at
a distance. And there's all these questions about whether פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah is קדשי מזבח, Kodshei Mizbeach, קדשי בדק הבית, Kodshei Bedek HaBayit,
and so on. Okay, but it's the sprinkling has to be facing
the opening of אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, but the שחיטה Shechitah it's
not explicit. But since it juxtaposes ושחט Veshachat and then it says
והזה, Vehizah, the דרשה Derashah is that the שחיטה Shechitah also has
to be facing the opening of אהל מועד. Ohel Moed.
So the גמרא Gemara says: וכי תימא דלא מקיש? Vechi Teima Dela
Makish? So maybe that's רב אדא בר אהבה, Rav Adda Bar Ahava,
but maybe רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't make that link, maybe רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't have that requirement. והאיתמר? Veha'itmar? But it was
taught, שחטה שלא כנגד הפתח, Shechtah Shelo Keneged Hapetch, let's say you
שחט Shecht it not facing the opening. רבי יוחנן אמר פסולה, Rabbi
Yochanan Amar Psulah, it's invalid. ושחט והזה. Veshachat Vehizah. It says you
shall slaughter and then it says you shall sprinkle towards אהל מועד,
Ohel Moed, so if the sprinkling has to be towards אהל מועד,
Ohel Moed, the שחיטה Shechitah does. וריש לקיש אמר כשרה. Veresh Lakish
Amar Kesherah. אל מחוץ למחנה ושחט. El Michutz Lamachaneh Veshachat. No,
it says bring it outside the camp and slaughter. Slaughter it, sprinkling
it towards אהל מועד Ohel Moed is already stage two and that
does not and so it is only the sprinkling that has to
be towards אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. ואיתמר נמי Veitmar nami and it
was also taught and some just teach this second teaching: שרפה שלא
כנגד הפתח, Sreifa shelo keneged hapetach, let's say the burning, you שחט
shecht it, you sprinkle, you burn. What's the story, where does the
burning have to take place? So what if the burning takes place
not in the place of the sprinkling of the blood, not facing
the אהל מועד Ohel Moed or the מקדש? Mikdash? ר' יוחנן אמר
פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan amar psula, it is invalid, and ר' אושעיא אמר
כשירה, Rabbi Oshaya amar ksheira, ר' אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya said it is
kosher. ר' יוחנן אמר פסולה, Rabbi Yochanan amar psula, ושרף והזה, Vesharaf
vehiza, you shall burn and sprinkle. Now that is actually not the
order. First it says והזה אל נכח פני אהל מועד מדמה שבע
פעמים vehiza el nochach pnei Ohel Moed midamah sheva pe'amim and then
the next פסוק pasuk says
ושרף את הפרה לעיניו. vesharaf et hapara le'enav. Nevertheless it is a
similar juxtaposition, שחיטה shechita and שריפה. sreifa. So where were we? ושרף
והזה Vesharaf vehiza and therefore if the sprinkling has to be, sprinkling
and שריפה. sreifa. So if the sprinkling has to be פני pnei
opposite אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, same with שחיטה, shechita, same with the
שריפה. sreifa. That is ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan linking the burning to
the sprinkling. ור' אושעיא אמר כשירה. VeRabbi Oshaya amar ksheira. No, it
is kosher. על פרשה ישרוף. Al pirsha yisrof. The פסוק pasuk about
burning it is a new פסוק pasuk and it says you burn
it with
the
פרש peresh which literally means together with the refuse, מקום שפרשה למיתה
שם תהא שרפתה. Makom sheporesha lemisa sham tehei srifatah. The place that
it separates to death, that is where you burn it, and where
it actually dies is not
necessarily where you do the sprinkling.
Could be you שחט shechted it in one place, it died there,
you moved to, you took the blood, you moved to face אהל
מועד Ohel Moed or the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you sprinkled it
facing the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and then you went back to
where you שחט shechted it and where it died and where the
body of the פרה Para still is, that is maybe a mile
away and it is not facing and in a different direction, and
there is where you burn it. The burning is where it dies,
it is not in the place where the sprinkling takes place. So
that is ר' אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. But ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says
it does have to be facing the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, the
burning, and presumably or explicitly the שחיטה. shechita. So why didn't he
give that as an example of not the right place of the
פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, not facing the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash? The
גמרא Gemara says like this: אמי,
איכא דאמרי לא מיבעיא קאמר. Ammi, ika de'amri lo mibaya ka'amar. It
goes without saying, meaning of course he could have said that but
he was telling you even a bigger חידוש. chiddush. לא מיבעיא חוץ
לחומה דריחוקי רחקה. Lo mibaya chutz lachoma dirchokei rachaka. It goes without
saying that if you שחט shechted it not in the right place,
that what constitutes not the right place and where I would have
had a הוה אמינא havah amina that you are חייב chayav for
שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz but the משנה Mishnah is telling you you
are not because it is a פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, so of
course if it is a place outside the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
and it is the wrong place of course you are not חייב
chayav for
שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. It is both further away and it is
a
פרה אדומה Para Aduma which is already something that does not come
to אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So there of course
you are פטור. patur. אלא אפילו לפנים מן החומה דקרובי קרבה ואימא
תתכשר קא משמע לן. Ella afilu liphnim min hachoma dekruvei karva ve'eima
tiskasher kamashmalan. To define what constitutes the invalid place of the פרה
אדומה Para Aduma it would be obvious to say that some place
that is
outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim and not facing אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, not
facing the מקדש, Mikdash, of course that is an invalid place for
the פרה אדומה, Para Aduma, ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan didn't even have
to mention that. He was telling you a חידוש, chiddush, that you
might have thought that if you bring it closer to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash maybe that constitutes a
כשר kosher place. Maybe only place that is outside of ירושלים Yerushalayim
and further away and not facing that is פסול, pasul, but maybe
getting closer that actually would be a כשר kosher place, קא משמע
לן kamashmalan that even that is a פסול pasul place. ר' יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan says to ריש לקיש Resh Lakish I don't agree with
you that you need to check it before it is פרה אדומה
Para Aduma and any place that is not checked is not a
כשר kosher place. If you want to know what a non-כשר kosher
place is for the פרה אדומה Para Aduma I'll give you two
examples. One is not facing the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, ריש לקיש
Resh Lakish might disagree with me but I think not facing is
not a כשר kosher place and I'll tell you even a bigger
חידוש. chiddush. You know what another case of not a כשר kosher
place is for the פרה אדומה? Parah Adumah? Inside ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And
that's what the משנה mishnah is talking about, one of those, if
you שחט shechted it and you might think it was שחוטי חוץ,
shechutei chutz, the answer is that it is not because the פרה
אדומה Parah Adumah is not fit for being brought to the מקדש.
Mikdash. Okay, קמשמע לן. Kamashmalan. אמר מר, Amar Mar, now we're going
to go back, so that's how we've explored what constitutes the non-appropriate
place for the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah and that nevertheless it's not
שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz because it's not fit for being brought as
a קרבן. korban. Now we're going to switch gears and get into
a little אגדי agadic section and we're going to talk about this
question of is ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael considered to be free of
unknown dead bodies? Okay, so let's take a look. אמר מר, Amar
Mar, אמר ליה amar leh רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, ולא כל ארץ ישראל בדוקה
היא? Velo kol Eretz Yisrael beduka hee? Is it not that all
of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you can assume that any, you know,
unmarked place is safe from dead bodies? So the גמרא Gemara says,
במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai Kamifligi? What is this debate? You know,
we don't want to assume it's just a מציאות metzius debate of
what the actual facts are. Where are they coming from that one
has an assumption that there's problems of possible dead bodies in unmarked
places and one has an assumption that it's not?
So the גמרא Gemara says, במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai Kamifligi? מר סבר ירד
מבול לארץ ישראל ומר סבר לא ירד. Mar savar yarad mabul l'Eretz
Yisrael u'mar savar lo yarad. The question is whether the מבול mabul
got to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or not. Okay, now the גמרא,
Gemara, you know, it says תחת כל השמים tachat kol hashamayim and
it's a little bizarre to think that the whole world flooded and
somehow I don't know there were magical walls that prevented ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael from flooding. And תוספות Tosafot even brings some, a, you
know, בראשית רבה Bereishit Rabbah that makes it sound that that would
be absurd to say something like that, but nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara
here is positing that it is possible that the מבול, mabul, the
floodwaters did not get to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Now how is
that relevant? Because the reason there would be a concern and in
general the גמרא Gemara treated, you know, this idea of טומאת ארץ
העמים Tumas Eretz Haamim that outside of Israel everything has to be
considered טמא, tamei, although there it ascribes it more to the practices
of the people of their time, but nevertheless, you know, wherever the
מבול mabul was, everybody died and their bodies got remained sort of,
you know, deep down like like trapped in the, in the mud,
and now they're underground and they're not marked. So all of that
has to be, you know, possibly it is a it is a
place where there are dead bodies. Only in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
if you say the waters didn't get to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael,
then ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is safe. Okay, that would be רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan who says all of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is
safe, and ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would say no, it flooded in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as well and the bodies are buried there
as well and therefore even ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is a problem.
Okay, so we, גמרא Gemara says, מר סבר ירד מבול לארץ ישראל
ומר סבר לא ירד. Mar savar yarad mabul l'Eretz Yisrael u'mar savar
lo yarad. It did not fall in Israel. אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו. U'shneihem mikra
echad darshu.
They're both debating, you know, coming off of the פסוק pasuk and
interpreting the same פסוק pasuk in a different way. בן אדם אמור
לה, Ben Adam emor lah, you know, this is a פסוק, pasuk,
you know, that God speaks to יחזקאל Yechezkel and says, you know,
בן אדם, Ben Adam, which is how the פסוקים, pesukim, you know,
talk to יחזקאל. Yechezkel. אמור לה את ארץ לא מטוהרה היא, Emor
lah at eretz lo metoharah hee,
you are a land that is not pure, לא גושמה ביום זעם,
lo gushmah beyom zaam, and you have not been rained upon in
the day of anger. So it's a little cryptic. So רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan סבר savar אתמוהי מתמה. itma'ei mitma'ei. So it's assumed to
be talking about Israel, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that it
is rhetorical קרא. kera. ארץ ישראל מי לא מטוהרה
את? Eretz Yisrael mi lo metoharah at? Land of Israel, are you
not not you are a טהור tahor land, are you not a
טהור tahor land? Of course you're a טהור tahor land. לא גושמה
ביום זעם. Lo gushmah beyom zaam. The rain didn't fall on you
in the day of anger at the מבול, mabul, and therefore the
people of מבול mabul didn't die and get buried in Israel. Now
the question is what do you mean, did the people living in
Israel live during the מבול? mabul? So we'll get back to that.
But for now anyway, it did not rain, the מבול mabul did
not reach there and therefore you do not have dead bodies buried
there and therefore are you not טהור? tahor? Of course you're טהור.
tahor. That's how רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan reads it. ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish סבר savar כפשטיה. kipshatei.
No,
you read it the simple way. את ארץ לא מטוהרה היא, At
eretz lo metoharah hee, it's a statement, you are not a טהור
tahor land. And well the second part is rhetorical, מי לא ירדו
עליך גשמים ביום זעם? Mi lo yardu alayich geshamim beyom zaam? Didn't
rain fall on you like it fell everywhere else in the day
of anger? And therefore there are similarly dead bodies buried in random
places in Israel as well. Now I should say that besides the
question we'll get to, which is didn't the people in Israel die
as well, there's also something interesting here that's not discussed by רש"י
Rashi or תוספות, Tosafot, which is if you have to be concerned
about bodies that are buried deep underground because of the what do
you call because of the מבול, mabul, then that means it's because
the טומאה tumah bursts through the ground and goes up. That's an
old principle we have about dead bodies. But we only say that
by Jewish bodies. We don't say it, at least the way the
הלכה halakhah is פסק, paskened, although there's a debate, that non-Jews, touching
their bodies or touching the bones causes טומאה, tumah, but not being
over them and not in direct contact. So that's A little strange
here because here the concern is פרה אדומה. para aduma. Nobody, you
know, there's no touching. It's just a question of what might be
buried below. Alright, that was not addressed. Maybe this גמרא Gemara is
going according to the opinion that even non-Jews' bodies cause טומאה tumah
through, you know, through just being over them. Alright, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay, איתיבי ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. Eitivei Resh Lakish le-Rabbi Yochanan. Now
they're going to try to prove it one way or the other
based on other פסוקים. pesukim. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish challenged רבי
יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. So remember, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is the one
that says that the waters did not get there on the מבול.
mabul. חצרות היו בירושלים בנויות על הסלע. Chatzerot hayu bi-Yerushalayim benuyot al
ha-sela. So here's what it talks about what they would do for
the פרה אדומה, para aduma, that they would have, you know, courtyards
in ירושלים Yerushalayim that were built on top of a rock. ותחתיהם
חלול Ve-tachtehem chalul and underneath the rock, imagine like an outcropping, there
would be air space. Okay, so there would be you'd be total
rock, nothing is buried in the rock, and then there wouldn't be
and then there would be an outcropping and there would be air
space. So even if, you know, you know, like a hundred feet
down where there's land, there's some dead body buried, because of the
outcropping, you know, it stops when it hits the underneath of the
rock and it doesn't, the טומאה, tumah, and it doesn't go through.
So anything on top of it is going to be טהור. tahor.
Alright, so בנויות על הסלע ותחתיהם חלול מפני קבר התהום benuyot al
ha-sela ve-tachtehem chalul mipnei kever ha-tehom
because of a possible buried body buried underneath that they were unaware
about. ומביאים נשים עוברות U-mevi'im nashim ubarot and they would bring pregnant
women there, you know, you hope they had a whole nice setup
there to take care of them. ויולדות Ve-yoldot and they would give
birth. ומגדלות שם בניהן לפרה U-megadlot sham beneihen le-para and they would
raise their kids to then do some of the work relating to
the פרה אדומה para aduma to sprinkle the ashes of the other
פרה אדומה para aduma on the כהן kohen that was going to
do the פרה. para. They were sort of very strict to try
to do this with a lot of stringencies because of a whole
debate that, you know, involved the צדוקים. Tzadokim. Okay, but so they
would go so far to raise kids that had never encountered טומאת
מת. tumat meit. Alright, and those to help them participate in the
sort of making of the ashes of the
פרה אדומה. para aduma. מביאים שוורים Mevi'im shevarim and they would bring,
you know, oxen. ועל גביהן דלתות Ve-al gabeihen dlatot and they would
have doors, you know, big planks of wood on the backs of
the
oxen. And ותינוקות יושבין עליהן ve-tinokot yoshvin aleihen and the kids would
sit on them once the kids now were raised. So, you know,
maybe they were five years old. תינוקות Tinokot doesn't mean literally a
baby. And so now they're bringing them. So these kids are raised
without ever having encountered טומאת מת. tumat meit. And then they have
to go and fill up the water from a wellspring that they're
going to use for the פרה אדומה. para aduma. So how do
they get them from this courtyard to the water? They bring oxen
and they have them sitting on like a plank on top of
the ox. Why? Because now when the ox is going to walk
from the חצר chatzer carrying the kid on the back to where
the wellspring is, if there's any
טומאה tumah underneath where the ox is walking, it'll hit the door
and the door, the underside of the door, and that will be
an אהל. ohel. That will be like a roof and that will
stop it from getting to the kid.
Okay, ותינוקות יושבין עליהן, ve-tinokot yoshvin aleihen, these kids would sit on
them. וכוסות של אבן בידם Ve-chosot shel even bi-yadam and they would
have
stone
vessels because stone because stone could not become טמא. tamei. ומילאו וישבו
במקומן U-mil'u ve-yashvu bi-mekoman and they would fill it up from the
wellspring and then go back to this courtyard. So bottom line is
you see that there was a concern of dead bodies buried. We
didn't say, oh, all of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is okay. So
there's an obvious answer to this. So אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע, Amar Rav Huna breih de-Rav Yehoshua, מעלה עשו בפרה. Ma'ala asu
be-para. No, these are just extra stringencies they're doing by פרה אדומה
para aduma because of a whole debate with the צדוקים. Tzadokim. This
is not technically required as a matter of הלכה. halacha. Now, ריש
לקיש Resh Lakish knows that. But ריש לקיש Resh Lakish might say
back, if there was no concerns of dead bodies,
then this would be absurd. This only makes sense if there's already
some concerns of dead bodies, so we can go overboard. That makes
sense. But maybe he's assuming it wouldn't make sense if there really
didn't exist a concern to begin with. But anyway, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan just says, no, this is just an extreme. This doesn't prove
anything.
Okay, איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש. Eitivei Rabbi Yochanan le-Resh Lakish. Now
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan challenged ריש לקיש Resh Lakish in the opposite
direction.
פעם אחת מצאו עצמות בלשכת דיר העצים. Pa'am achat matzu atzamot be-lishkat
deir ha-etzim. So there was one time where they found bones, you
know, like a human bones
in this chamber where they would have the wood for the altar.
This was in the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. Okay.
וביקשו לגזור טומאה על ירושלים. U-vikshu ligzor tumah al Yerushalayim. And then
they wanted to say we're going to have to treat all of
ירושלים Yerushalayim as טמא. tamei. You know, that's a bit of an
overreaction. But look, they had evidence once that even the place that
maybe they thought was the most pure underneath the בית המקדש Beit
Ha-Mikdash they found some bones. Alright, now it doesn't say that it
was in the ground underneath the בית המקדש. Beit Ha-Mikdash. It says,
you know, maybe somebody had died there in the corner and nobody,
I don't know what
happened. but all right, whatever it is.
So, I'm sorry, so where are we? So, this is a תוספתא
Tosefta by the way. So, and because they decreed טומאה tumah on
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, עמד רבי יהושע על רגליו, amad Rabbi Yehoshua al raglav,
so Rabbi Yehoshua stood up, ואמר לא בושה וכלימה לנו, ve'amar lo
busha vechalima lanu, wouldn't this be a shame and embarrassment to us
שנגזר טומאה על עיר אבותינו, shenigzar tumah al ir avoteinu, that we
should, we should, you know, decree that the holy city of ירושלים
Yerushalayim we're going to treat it all as possibly טמא, tamei, okay,
or treat it as טמא tamei rabbinically? And I'll prove to you
that that's not an issue. איה מתי מבול איה מתי נבוכדנצר? Ayei
metei mabul, ayei metei Nevuchadnezzar? Where are the dead of, you know,
from the מבול? mabul? Where are the dead of, you know, of
נבוכדנצר? Nevuchadnezzar? Meaning it seems to be sort of be saying like,
you know, if you were going to be concerned about it, you
could read that in a couple ways, but I'll read it as:
if you were going to be concerned about it, then you should
have been concerned a long time ago because people did die here,
people died in the
מבול, mabul, people died in the time of נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, and obviously
it was when they were being exiled they were being killed by
נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. So, you know, if you thought there was something to
worry, you had plenty to worry about before. Why weren't you worried
about it? Because whatever was needed to be done to remove them,
or maybe they never even, you know, we'll get to that, whatever
was needed to be done was done. They're not here, so let's,
you know, we obviously are taking steps to make sure ירושלים Yerushalayim
is טהור. tahor. We are not going to declare ירושלים Yerushalayim to
be טמא. tamei. Now, מדקאמר הכי, mideikamar hachi, so now how do
you interpret this "where are they?" So Rabbi Yochanan says from the
fact that he said that,
מדקאמר
הכי לאו למימר דלא הוו?
mideikamar hachi lav
lemeimar delo havu? Isn't he basically saying, look, you know, even the
dead of the מבול, mabul, even the מבול mabul nobody died here.
Of course ירושלים Yerushalayim is טהור. tahor. Now by the way, we're
only sort of talking about ירושלים, Yerushalayim, we're not talking about all
of ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But okay, anyway, it sounds like, says
Rabbi Yochanan, that he's saying the מתי מבול metei mabul didn't die
here. This place is טהור. tahor. So the Gemara says no, that
can't be what he means.
So, דלא הוו? delo havu? So the Gemara says ולטעמך הרוגי נבוכדנצר
הכא נמי דלא הוו? uletameich harugei Nevuchadnezzar hacha nami delo havu? What
do you mean? You know, נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar definitely slaughtered Jews in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim. אלא הוו ופינו הכא נמי הוו ופינו. Ela havu upinnu hacha
nami havu upinnu. So he's saying the only way to make sense,
you know, is okay, dead people died here. That's what, you know,
Rabbi Yehoshua is saying, but in the time of נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, but
the bodies were removed. We kept ירושלים Yerushalayim טהור. tahor. So if
that's true, he's saying the same thing about the מבול. mabul. They
died here but we removed their bodies. So if anything, it's an
evidence to Resh Lakish that the מבול mabul did get to ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ואי אפנו, ve'i ipnu, so now the Gemara says
okay, but one minute. אלא ואי אפנו אפנו. ela ve'i ipnu ipnu.
So before we get to how this is a proof to Resh
Lakish, which it seems to be because it's saying reasonably they did
die here but they were removed, the Gemara's saying wait, wait, wait.
Besides the question of whether the dead of the מבול mabul died
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the מבול mabul happened in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, the bigger debate of Resh Lakish and Rabbi Yochanan is
whether ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is considered to be free from dead
bodies. So if in the end of the day Resh Lakish reads
this statement of Rabbi Yehoshua, when Rabbi Yehoshua is saying like where
are the dead of the מבול, mabul, where are the dead of
נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, they're not here because we cleaned them out. So if
that's what he's saying, why is he concerned about dead bodies? They've
been cleaned out. So the Gemara says הא איפני. ha ipni. So
if they cleaned them out, they cleaned them out. Why is Resh
Lakish, but forget the מבול mabul for a minute, you know, Rabbi
Yehoshua is here saying God forbid we should be גוזר טומאה, gozer
tumah, everything was cleaned out, so why is Resh Lakish concerned about
טומאה tumah in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael?
So the Gemara says, no, דאיהי דאפני מירושלים מכולא ארץ ישראל לא
אפני. de'ihi de'ifni mi'Yerushalayim mikol Eretz Yisrael lo ifni. No, no, no,
Rabbi Yehoshua is, you know, saying we cleaned them out of ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, but we didn't clean them out of all of Israel. So
bottom line what Resh Lakish is saying is you Rabbi Yochanan think
that that's a proof to your side that he's saying where are
the dead of the מבול, mabul, that's not what he's saying. He's
saying people died in ירושלים Yerushalayim but we cleaned it out, ירושלים
Yerushalayim is clean from
טומאה. tumah. Elsewhere in the rest of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael things
are still a problem, but here in ירושלים Yerushalayim we cleaned it
out. So if anything, it's a proof to me. Which now the
Gemara turns around and says: איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, so others say
איתיבי ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן, eitibi Resh Lakish le'Rabbi Yochanan, Resh Lakish
was the one who cited this source and actually the obvious sort
of reading of the source is a challenge to Rabbi Yochanan.
איה מתי מבול איה מתי נבוכדנצר? Ayei metei mabul, ayei metei Nevuchadnezzar?
That's the quote of Rabbi Yehoshua. מאי לאו מדיהני הוו הני נמי
הוו? Mai lav mideihanei havu hanei nami havu? So since the dead
of נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, what he's saying is okay, people died in ירושלים
Yerushalayim at the time of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar and it's been cleaned out,
so presumably he's saying the same thing about the מבול. mabul. People
died in the מבול mabul and it's been cleaned out. So the
Gemara says no, מידי איריא, midei irya, is that a proof? הא
כדאיתא והא כדאיתא. ha kide'isa veha kide'isa. Maybe רבי יהושע *Rebbe Yehoshua*
is saying two different points. First of all, ירושלים Yerushalayim, *Yerushalayim* stays
טהור *tahor*. When the מבול mabul *Mabul* came, they never even died
here, the מבול mabul. *Mabul* didn't even get here. So that's one
way it stays טהור *tahor*. The other way is even when people
died here, like Nebuchadnezzar, they were cleaned out. I don't think that's
a פשט *pshat*, I mean clearly they seem to be one statement,
but okay. So you can't prove from this whether or not the
מבול mabul *Mabul* got to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael, *Eretz Yisrael*. And
even if ירושלים *Yerushalayim* is בדוקה *beduka*, we've just said that פרה
אדומה *Parah Adumah* has to be taken out of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. So
the question really is the status of Israel outside of ירושלים *Yerushalayim*.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says like this: איתיבי *Eisvei*:
מכל אשר בחרבה מתו *mikol asher becharava meisu*. So now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to sort of bring the פסוקים pesukim. *pesukim*
not between ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* and רבי יוחנן *Reb
Yochanan*. It says everything on the land died. בשלמא לדידי *bishlama ledidi*,
so this is still ריש לקיש Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish*, I'm sorry,
this is still ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* talking. בשלמא לדידי *bishlama ledidi*
it works according to me, דאמינא ירד מבול mabul לארץ ישראל *de'amina
yarad mabul le'Eretz Yisrael*, that the מבול mabul *Mabul* came to Israel,
משום הכי מתו *mishum hachi meisu*. So that's what it says: everybody
on dry land died. That's פשט *pshat* of the פסוקים *pesukim*. Dry
land, that includes Israel, okay? That reads well according to me, says
ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. אלא Ela, לדידך *ela ledidach*, but according to
you רבי יוחנן *Reb Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Reb Yochanan*, אמאי מתו *amai
meisu*? Why did everybody die on the land? Why did they die
in Israel as well, in the land of Israel? So he says,
משום הבלא *mishum hevla*. You're right. They didn't die because of the
waters of the מבול mabul *Mabul*, but because the מבול Mabul. *Mabul*
was happening in the rest of the world, the, you know, sulfur
and the heat and whatever that was in the atmosphere, that killed
everybody. So everybody in Israel died, everybody other than נח *Noach* and
his family died, okay, but the מבול Mabul *Mabul* still didn't reach
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael. *Eretz Yisrael*. Now you're probably asking: one minute.
The whole point was that ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* you don't have
to worry about dead bodies because the מבול Mabul *Mabul* didn't reach
it. But now רבי יוחנן *Reb Yochanan* is conceding, because it's a
פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, that people, everybody died in the land of Israel
at the time of the מבול *Mabul*. So why don't you have
to worry about dead bodies? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says: אהא *aha*.
Since they died on dry land, eventually their bones could be found
and they could be then go ahead and buried, and then the
graves would be marked. But if they died in the מבול *Mabul*,
they got, you know, it all got buried in the mud underground
and then there were no bodies that were visible, and that's why
we don't know where those bodies are. Okay, so that's obviously a
very difficult read of the פסוקים *pesukim*, that ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*
was saved from the waters of the מבול *Mabul*. Okay, כדרב חסדא
*kederav Chisda*. Now this idea that there was all of this heat
in the atmosphere and it killed everybody even who, you know, even
if they were not hit by the waters in the land of
Israel, that is like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. דאמר רב חסדא *de'amar
Rav Chisda* because רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* says ברותחין קלקלו וברותחין נידונו
*beroschin kilkelu uveroschin nidonu*. They sinned with hot liquid, meaning the sin
of, it was assumed to be the sin of עריות arayos *arayos*,
of, you know, illicit sexual activity, maybe also specifically about זרע לבטלה
*zera levatala*, about masturbation. That's, you know, that's a דרשה *drasha* the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* has elsewhere. And therefore they were punished by boiling
hot water. All right, or נידונו *nidonu*. דכתיב הכא וישכו המים *dechsiv
hacha vayashoku hamayim*. The waters settled, but he's also reading it as
like they cooled down. וכתיב התם וחמת המלך שככה *vechasiv hasam vachamas
hamelech shachacha*, the heat of the king, the anger of the king
abated. So they were hot and steamy, and that would have killed
everybody in the land of Israel even if waters did not get
there, and then as רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, their bodies would have
been buried and marked afterwards by נח *Noach* or his descendants. Okay,
איכא דאמרי *ika de'amri*.
So that was a way ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* could challenge רבי
יוחנן *Reb Yochanan*. Others say, איתיבי רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש *Eisvei Reb
Yochanan leReish Lakish*. No, it starts the other way. רבי יוחנן *Reb
Yochanan* challenged ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish*. מכל אשר בחרבה מתו *mikol asher
becharava meisu*. Everybody on dry land died. בשלמא לדידי *bishlama ledidi*, that
works well according to me, says רבי יוחנן *Reb Yochanan*, דאמינא לא
ירד מבול לארץ ישראל *de'amina lo yarad mabul le'Eretz Yisrael*, that it
didn't get to the land of Israel, משום הכי הוי חרבה *mishum
hachi havei charava*. Therefore there were people on dry land, the people
in Israel, and they died. Okay. אלא לדידך *ela ledidach*, but according
to you, מאי חרבה *mai charava*? What does it mean everybody on
dry land died? There was no dry land! Okay,
it's a good question but the answer is obvious. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says: No, חרבה שהיתה מעיקרא *charava shehaysa me'ikara*. It means
what was dry land until the מבול *Mabul* started. Okay, so what
does it coming therefore to spell out or to indicate? Why doesn't
it just say everybody died? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: ואמאי
קרי ליה חרבה *ve'amai kari lei charava*? Why does it point out
dry land, if now it's no longer dry land? כדרב חסדא *kederav
Chisda*, like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*. דאמר רב חסדא *de'amar Rav Chisda*:
בדור המבול לא נגזרה גזירה על הדגים *bedor hamabul lo nigzera gezeira
al hadagim*. That the fish were not punished because it says, ודגים
שבים shebayam. *vedagim shebayam*, the fish in the seas. שנאמר she'ne'emar, *shene'emar*:
מכל אשר בחרבה מתו *mikol asher becharava meisu*. All live things that
were living on land died. It affected land animals and humans, okay,
but not those in the sea. ולא דגים שבים *velo dagim shebayam*.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: בשלמא למאן דאמר לא ירד
מבול לארץ ישראל *bishlama leman de'amar lo yarad mabul le'Eretz Yisrael*. According
to the position of רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that the מבול *mabbol*
did not come to the Land of Israel, היינו דקם רימא Reima
התם *hainu d'kam reima hasam*.
So therefore the רימא Reima. *reima*, which is a very large animal,
it was able to survive because it walked over to the Land
of Israel and maybe the הבלא *hevla* didn't hurt it. Okay, like
you could sort of say, you know, what happened to the elephants?
Where was, you know, how did they fit all these large animals
on the תיבה teiva. *teiva*? So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* actually says,
well, it understands that there was one extremely large animal of almost
mythic proportions as we'll see. How did it survive? Oh, according to
me, according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, it survived by going to
Israel. Now רש"י *Rashi* says רימא *reima* here means the ראם re'eim
*re'em* that is meant in the פסוקים *pesukim* like קרני ראם re'eim
קרניו *karnei re'em karnav*, okay. תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot*, you know, quotes a
תרגום אונקלוס *Targum Onkelos* on the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in דברים *Devarim*
where it speaks about the kosher animals, so it says ואקו ודישון
*v'ako v'dishon*. So the אונקלוס *Onkelos* says on ואקו ודישון *v'ako v'dishon*,
ויעלא ורימא *v'yala v'reima*. So it's the רימא *reima* is not a
ראם re'eim *re'em*, it is a דישון *dishon*, whatever a דישון *dishon*
is. So we'll see in a minute in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
about so let's about its mythic proportions. Okay, so רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* says, oh, according to me, I understand how this enormous animal
could survive. It went to ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*. Or the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, according to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* that makes sense.
אלא למאן דאמר *ella l'man d'amar*—אלא *ella*—ירד מבול
*yarad mabbol*—but according to the one that says that it flooded even
in Israel, רימא היכי קם *reima heichi kam*? Where did the רימא
*reima* go? You know, how did it survive? It certainly couldn't have
fit on the ark. So אמר רבי ינאי *amar Rabbi Yannai*, גוריות
הכניסו בתיבה *guriot hichnisu b'teiva*. They brought in little baby רימא *reimas*
into the ark and they could fit. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says ואמר רבה בר בר חנה *v'amar Rabba bar bar Chana*, לדידי
חזי לי אורזילא דרימא בת יומא Yoma *l'didi chazi li orzila d'reima
bas yoma*. I saw this אורזילא *orzila* of a רימא *reima*, which
is basically like a child of the רימא *reima* that was one
day old, this questions exactly what the גרסא *gersa* is. But whatever,
I saw this baby רימא *reima* one day old והוי כטור תבור
*v'havi k'tur tavor*, and it was as large as the Mount Tabor.
בר תבור כמה הוי *bar tavor kama havei*? And how big is
that? ארבעין פרסי *arba'in parsi*, 40 parsangs. A parsang is about 4
kilometers. You do the math, 160 kilometers. משכא דצואריה תלתא פרסי *mashcha
d'tzavarei tlata parsai*,
and the length of its neck was three parsangs, 12 kilometers. מרבעתא
דרישא פרסא ופלגא *marvasa d'reisha parsa u'palga*, where it would lay down
its head a parsang and a half, okay, six kilometers. So בקיצור
*be-kitzur*, how could even and that was a baby. So even the
babies couldn't fit on the ark. Clearly this is some mythic creature.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually
thought it existed because it's asking how did it survive the flood.
So, and I'm sorry, the end of the statement is כרכא וסכר
ירדנא *karcha v'sachar Yardna*. And when it, you know, defecated, you know,
its refuse even sealed up the Jordan River. It was so large
it stopped the river from flowing. Okay, so anyway, how could it
have survived by getting even a baby one wouldn't fit on the
ark? So אמר רבי יוחנן *amar Rabbi Yochanan*, so רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* says, ראשו הכניסו לתיבה *rosho hichnisu l'teiva*. No, it was fine.
It was basically all swimming in the waters or maybe it was
so big it was standing on the land that was way way
down there, and but it had to breathe, so its head was
in the ark and that allowed it to breathe. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, one minute, we just said even where it
needs to land its head is a parsang and a half. ואמר
מר מרבעתא דרישא פרסא ופלגא *v'amar mar marvasa d'reisha parsa u'palga*? But
we just said the place where to lay down its head was
a parsang and a half? אלא ראש חוטמו הכניסו לתיבה *ella rosh
chotamo hichnisu l'teiva*. Fine. It stuck its nose into the ark, so
it's like its nose above water. But basically I guess it couldn't
stand on the stuff below, so it needed to be held by
the ark so it was, you know, floating on the water and
it could breathe because the nose was still in the ark.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואמר רבי יוחנן לא ירד
מבול לארץ ישראל *v'amar Rabbi Yochanan lo yarad mabbol l'Eretz Yisrael*. So
why is רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* giving this answer? רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* himself says the מבול *mabbol* didn't get to ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael* so he could say the רימא *reima* went to ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael*. So the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says no, לדיברי ריש לקיש
קאמר *l'divrei Reish Lakish q'amar*. He's saying it to help defend ריש
לקיש *Reish Lakish*. That's what ריש לקיש *Reish Lakish* could say. So
now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to see if it likes
this answer that the nose is how it survived. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says והא קסגיא תיבה *v'ha kasagya teiva*, but the ark
is going up and down and up and down, so its nose
would like slip off. It wouldn't be able to, you know, and
it's going to drown. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says אמר ריש
לקיש קרניו קשרו בתיבה *amar Reish Lakish karnav kishru b'teiva*. No, they
like used, they tied its horns to the ark so it would
go up and down with the ark and it was able to
still keep its head above water. It was basically a life preserver
for it. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ואמר רב חסדא
אנשי דור המבול ברותחין קלקלו ברותחין נידונו *v'amar Rav Chisda anshei dor
hamabbol b'roschin kilkalu b'roschin nidonu*. And we just quoted רב חסדא *Rav
Chisda* above that spoke about, you know, the boiling hot water. So,
you know, again, maybe the heat that got there to the Land
of Israel wasn't enough to kill it. But being immersed in this
boiling hot water, shouldn't that have killed it? So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ולטעמיך *u'l'ta'ameich*, if one minute says the גמרא *Gemara*, if
you're going to worry about the hot water, there's other things to
worry about as well. תיבה היכי סגי, how could the Ark have
survived? They put it with pitch, the pitch would have melted off
in the hot water. So how did that not happen? ועוד, Ve'od,
עוג מלך הבשן היכי קאי? Og Melech Habashan heichi kai? And if
עוג מלך הבשן, Og Melech Habashan, we know the מדרש midrash says
that he survived by hanging on to the Ark, how come he
wasn't dissolved by the boiling hot water? So where are we? היכי
קאי. Heichi kai. אלא, נס נעשה להם, nes na'aseh lahem, it was
a miracle, שנתצננו בצידי התיבה, shenitztanenu betzidei hateiva,
the water right around the Ark, you know, there was like a
special sphere protecting the Ark and the water right around it stayed
cool. And that's where עוג Og hung on and that's why the
pitch stayed on and that's why this רימא could have bobbed its
head and survived. Okay. Anyway, בצידי התיבה. betzidei hateiva.
So that, we're done now with the רימא. Now before we go
on,
I just want to read to a תוספות Tosafos here, because this
תוספות Tosafos ארזילא דרימא, arzila dereima, תוספות Tosafos says the following.
He says like this, he says, ואותם, ve'osam, one, two, three,
four lines down in the narrow lines, the line starts with the
word שבים. He says, ואותם באלוס שאנו קוראים ראם, ve'osam bafalos she'anu
korim re'eim,
so now we have buffaloes which we call ראם re'eim and if
you say רימה reima is ראם re'eim is the same thing, so
ליתא, lessa, that is actually those are not the ראם re'eim and
not the רימה, reima, whatever, but not the ראם re'eim of the
תורה. Torah. Because the ראם re'eim, of the תורה Torah or the
רימה reima certainly is a חיה, chaya, and this תוספות Tosafos, is
saying buffaloes are a בהמה. beheima. And that matters. Why? Because since
it's a בהמה, beheima, וחלבם אסור, vachelvam assur, their חלב cheilev is
forbidden. Buffaloes are a בהמה, beheima, are in the class of domesticated
animals just like, you know, cows are, and they're not in the
class of wild animals. Fascinating debate whether buffaloes are a חיה chaya
or a בהמה. beheima. Okay. ראם ודאי מן חיה הוא, Re'eim vadai
min chaya hu, because we know the ראם re'eim is a חיה
chaya וחלבו מותר, vachelvo mutar, and its חלב cheilev is permissible. כדיכתיב
איל וצבי ויחמור ואקו ודישון, kedi'chsiv ayal u'tzvi ve'yachmur ve'akko vedishon, מתרגמינן
ויעלא ורימא, metargeminan ve'yala u'reima, okay, and that's the פסוק pasuk that
lists kosher animals that are חיות, chayot, okay, and רימה, reima, ראם
re'eim etc. So and so that would, so if a buffalo was
a ראם, re'eim its חלב cheilev would be מותר. muttar. How do
we know that it's not a חיה? chaya? So he says, ובאלוס
שבמקומנו קטנים, u'vafalos shebimkomeinu ketanim,
and because buffaloes are small, they could easily fit in the תיבה.
So don't go, this is going to lead to a big איסור.
issur. You're going to call the buffaloes a ראם re'eim and you're
going to think it's this רימה reima and the רימה reima is
a חיה chaya and you're going to eat their חלב. cheilev. It's
not true. Buffaloes are not the ראם and they're not a חיה.
chaya. Okay, and it's actually and just as a little evidence about
why not just because they're small so they could have fit in
the Ark, but in terms of the definition of חיה chaya and
בהמה, beheima, take a look at the end of תוספות, Tosafos he
says, ועוד, ve'od, הכחזינא דאותם באלוס בני מלאכה נינהו, hakechazina de'osam bafalos
benei melacha ninhu,
we see that you can use them to do work, ומושכין בקרון
וחורשין בהם, u'moshkin bekaron ve'chorshin bahem, you can use them to plow
and you can use them to pull a wagon, okay, וראם לאו
בר מלאכה הוא, ve're'eim lav bar melacha hu, and a ראם is
not something, is an undomesticatable
beast. So what's considered בהמה beheima is not just whether it has
been domesticated, but whether it sort of can be domesticated. Okay, and
anyway, so buffaloes according to תוספות are a בהמה beheima not a
חיה chaya and they are not the ראם of the פסוקים. All
right, back to the גמרא.
So now the גמרא says like this. ולריש לקיש ניחא דירד מבול
לארץ ישראל, u'l'Reish Lakish niha de'yarad mabul l'Eretz Yisrael, so
according to ריש לקיש said the גמרא, it's fine that the מבול
went to ארץ ישראל, והלא פש, v'halo pash, but one minute, why
is he bothered about dead bodies? The dead bodies did not stay
in Israel that were dissolved or you know destroyed in the מבול.
How do you know that? דאמר ריש לקיש, D'amar Reish Lakish, because
ריש לקיש himself said, למה נקרא שמה מצולה? lama nikra shemah Metzula?
Why is בבל Bavel called מצולה Metzula which is like a swamp?
שכל מתי מבול נצטללו לשם, shekol meteis mabul nitztelelu l'sham, because all
the dead of the מבול you know sort of floated there. בבל
Bavel was lower than all of the lands, this is something the
גמרא sort of says and all of the bodies in the מבול
were brought to בבל. Bavel. So they didn't stay in Israel. So
the גמרא says, למה נקרא שמה שנער? lama nikra shemah Shinar?
Why is בבל Bavel called שנער? Shinar? שכל מתי מבול ננערו לשם,
shekol meteis mabul ninaru l'sham, all the dead of the מבול were
like overturned there, you know tumbled there. Either way they didn't stay,
so why are you so bothered that the מבול came to Israel
there and why are you bothered about dead bodies?
So the גמרא says, אי אפשר דלא אידבקו. ee efshar delo idbeku.
No, no, some were still going to be stuck in the mud.
You know, it doesn't mean all every single body went there, most
of them wound up being washed away to בבל, Bavel, some certainly
remained still stuck in the mud in ארץ ישראל.
Okay. אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rebbe Abbahu, למה נקרא שמה שנער? lama
nikra shemah Shinar? Now we're just going to wrap this whole thing
up with a discussion of the name of בבל. Bavel. בבל Bavel
and שנער Shinar and the dead of the מבול. Why is it
called שנער? Shinar? שכל מתי מבול ננערו... shekol metei mabul ninaru... I'm
sorry, I skipped back. שמנערת עשיריה. shemenaeret ashireha.
That it like empties itself of its wealthy people. All right, so
that the wealthy people do not manage to... there's not a lot
of wealth in בבל, Bavel, רש"י says because they do not have
compassion on people. All right, quotes another גמרא. So והא חזינא דהוו,
veha chazina dehavu,
but one minute, we see there are wealthy people in בבל. Bavel.
תלתא דרי לא משתי, tlata darei lo mashti, no, but it doesn't
get sustained for up to three generations. Okay, אמר רבי אמי, Amar
Rabbi Ami, כל האוכל מעפרה של בבל, kol haochel meafara shel Bavel,
one last point about this, anybody that eats from the dirt of
בבל, Bavel, כאילו אוכל בשר אבותיו, keilu ochel besar avotav, you're eating
from the flesh of your fathers because all of the dead bodies
of the מבול got there and got disintegrated so it's all mixed
up with all the dirt. So don't go eating from the dirt
of בבל. Bavel. ויש אומרים כאילו אוכל שקצים ורמשים, veyeish omrim keilu
ochel shkatzim uremasim, and some say it's like you eat like rodents
and bugs and so on. רש"י also ties this to, you know,
everything died in the מבול including all these disgusting rodents and bugs.
Fine, that was the end of that long Aggadic discussion. Now we'll
just do one or two more pieces here about that goes back
to our משנה. Mishnah. שעיר המשתלח, Se'ir Hamishtaleach,
another thing you're not חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz is
the goat that you send off to the עזאזל Azazel on יום
כיפור Yom Kippur because that is not something that is brought to
the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So the גמרא says, ורמינהי, ureminhi, I'll
ask you on this, we have a מדרש הלכה: Midrash Halacha: או
קרבן, O Korban, it's going on the question when the פסוק pasuk
says and you didn't bring it, this thing that you shechted outside
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, להקריב קרבן לה', lehakriv korban l'Hashem, to
bring a קרבן korban to God. And it says, you know, maybe
that word קרבן korban שומע אני אפילו קדשי בדק הבית, shomea ani
afilu kodshei bedek habayis, maybe it includes even animals that were sanctified
to the Temple treasury and not sanctified as a קרבן korban because
קרבן korban can include gifts and not only sacrifices. Where do you
know that? שנקראו קרבן, shenikru korban, שנאמר, ונקרב את קרבן ה', vanakreiv
et korban Hashem, we brought the קרבן ה', korban Hashem, you know,
all the gold or whatever, the booty that they got from מדין.
Midian. So how do you know that it says it wasn't brought
as a קרבן, korban, maybe it means, you know, even something that
was an animal that was to be given to the Temple treasury
is included in the איסור issur of שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. So
the גמרא says, תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, I mean the מדרש הלכה,
Midrash Halacha, ואל פתח אהל מועד לא הביאו. v'el petach Ohel Moed
lo hevi'o. It was not brought to the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed.
מי שראוי לבוא באהל מועד, Mi sheraui lavo b'Ohel Moed,
only something that should be brought into the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed,
יצא קדשי בדק הבית שאינם ראויים, yatza kodshei bedek habayis she'einam reuyim,
it excludes things that are sanctified for the Temple treasury that you
do not bring them, you do not bring an animal that ultimately
you're going to cash out and use the money and so on,
you know, it's not there to be brought into the אהל מועד
Ohel Moed and therefore it is not a problem of שחוטי חוץ.
shechutei chutz. Okay, שאינם ראויים. she'einam reuyim. הוציא את אלו שאינם ראויים
ולא הוציא את שעיר המשתלח שהוא ראוי לבוא לפתח אהל מועד, Hotzi
et elu she'einam reuyim velo hotzi et se'ir hamishtaleach shehu raui lavo
l'petach Ohel Moed,
maybe I will exclude these which don't have any business being in
the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, but I won't exclude the שעיר המשתלח
se'ir hamishtaleach which does have a business being in the אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. Why? Because that's where it started. You bring both of
the goats and you, you know, you do the lottery. So it
does start in the אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. So maybe by the
שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach which does start in the אהל מועד Ohel
Moed maybe you are חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ? shechutei chutz? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, לה'... l'Hashem...
it says to bring a קרבן korban לה', l'Hashem, והוציא שעיר המשתלח
שאינו מיוחד לה'. v'hotzi se'ir hamishtaleach she'eino meyuchad l'Hashem. That excludes the
שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach which is not going to לה', l'Hashem, it's
going לעזאזל. l'Azazel. So we're not going to get into the whole
theology of that, but bottom line is, here's something that is ראוי
raui for אהל מועד Ohel Moed but it's not fully לה'. l'Hashem.
So the גמרא says, okay, so both this and our משנה Mishnah
says you're exempt by the שעיר המשתלח. se'ir hamishtaleach. But this says
it's fit for אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, the exclusion is לה'. l'Hashem.
Our משנה Mishnah says it's not fit for אהל מועד. Ohel Moed.
What's the story? So the גמרא says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, כאן
קודם הגורל כאן לאחר הגורל. kan kodem hagoral kan achar hagoral. No,
no, no, it's before or after the lots are drawn. Until the
lots are drawn, it's, you know, it's fit for
אהל מועד Ohel Moed because, you know, you have to do the
drawing of the lots. Once the lots are drawn, it's no longer
fit, now you have to send it out and therefore it's excluded
by the פסוק pasuk of not being fit.
But before, when it is fit for אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, it's
only excluded by the פסוק pasuk, of לה'. l'Hashem. So the גמרא
says, לאחר הגורל נמי איכא וידוי, achar hagoral nami ika vidui, wait
a minute, it doesn't stop belonging in אהל מועד Ohel Moed after
the lots, you still have to do the וידוי. vidui. So the
גמרא says fine, אלא אמר רב מני, ela amar Rav Mani, לא
קשיא, lo kashya, כאן קודם וידוי כאן לאחר וידוי. kan kodem vidui
kan achar vidui. Fine, that's the line. So until you do the
וידוי vidui by this, you know, you basically you drew the lots
because it's actually a question you should have asked, until you draw
the lots, how do you know
which is the שעיר המשתלח? se'ir hamishtaleach? So actually there's another גמרא
in יומא that says you have these two goats, you're planning on
using them for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but if you shechted them
outside the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you know, you're actually חייב chayav
for שחוטי חוץ shechutei chutz because until you draw the lots, A,
you don't know which is לה' l'Hashem and which is לעזאזל, l'Azazel,
and B, you could use both of them for some other קרבן,
korban, from a, you know, you don't know, so until you draw
the lots they're not
fit. You go into the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, okay, you draw
the lots, okay, and now you're פטור. patur. Why are you פטור?
patur? Because even though they're still פתח אהל מועד, Pesach Ohel Moed,
you have to do the וידוי, viduy, you're not—the one that's לעזאזל,
l'Azazel, okay, is not להשם. la'Hashem. All right, so you're פטור patur
on the לעזאזל l'Azazel because it's not להשם. la'Hashem. Then you do
the וידוי, viduy, and then there's another reason you're פטור patur on
the one לעזאזל. l'Azazel. It's now it's also not even ראוי ra'uy
for אהל מועד Ohel Moed anymore. Now you've done the וידוי, viduy,
now it has to get sent out of the אהל מועד. Ohel
Moed. Okay, we'll read one more. הרובע והנרבע. ha-rovei'a v'ha-nirba.
So, you know, an animal that's been—that's acted in bestiality, that is
no longer, you know, that's not ראוי ra'uy for פתח אהל מועד
Pesach Ohel Moed and that's also excluded. And the גמרא's only concern
with this is the פסוק pasuk that it excludes it from, because
it says לפני משכן השם. lifnei mishkan Hashem. It wasn't satisfied by
saying it's not fit for אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. It needed an
extra phrase of לפני משכן השם. lifnei mishkan Hashem. And the גמרא
wants to say, why can't you just say that these animals are
not fit for אהל מועד? Ohel Moed? So let's take a look.
והנמי תיפוק ליה מפתח אהל מועד? v'hani nami tipok lei mi-pesach ohel
moed? Why not just learn it out from the idea of פתח
אהל מועד? Pesach Ohel Moed? So we'll continue here on ק״ד ע״א.
kuf yud daled amud aleph. בשלמא רובע ונרבע משכחת לה דאקדישינהו מעיקרא
והדר רבעו. bishlama rovei'a v'nirba mashkachat lah de'akdishinhu mei'ikara ve'hadar rav'o.
So I get that you can have a scenario by the act
of bestiality where at least the animal at one time was fit
for אהל מועד. Ohel Moed. You sanctified it as a קרבן, korban,
and now it's fit for אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, and now an
act of bestiality was done. So you might think, ah, maybe this
counts in the category of ראוי לאהל מועד ra'uy l'ohel moed because
at least earlier it was ראוי, ra'uy, and maybe I will be
חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. So you have an extra
פסוק, pasuk לפני משכן השם, lifnei mishkan Hashem, which shows you since
now it's not fit, it doesn't matter that it was before. Okay,
good. I understand why you need that special פסוק pasuk, for רובע
ונרבע, rovei'a v'nirba, because you could have had a case where at
least one stage in its life it was fit for אהל מועד.
Ohel Moed. But אלא מוקצה ונעבד, ela muktzeh v'ne'evad, let's go to
the next cases in the משנה. Mishna. Set aside for עבודה זרה
avodah zarah or worshipped for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. אין אדם אוסר
דבר שאינו שלו. ein adam oser davar she'eino shelo. Once you sanctified
them, if you worship it for עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, you don't
change its status. It's no longer yours. So those should—the only scenario
of מוקצה ונעבד, muktzeh v'ne'evad, of worship where it's forbidden, is when
you did it before you sanctified. So then just exclude it based
on ראוי לאהל מועד. ra'uy l'ohel moed. Why did you need this
extra thing, which seems to imagine a scenario where it started fit
and became unfit? So how do you get that case? So the
גמרא says, בקדשים קלים ואליבא דרבי יוסי הגלילי דאמר קדשים קלים ממון
בעלים הוא. b'kodshim kalim v'aliba d'Rabbi Yosi HaGelili d'amar kodshim kalim mamon
be'alim hu. Ah, it's רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yosi HaGelili that says
by קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, like a שלמים, shlamim, since you can
eat the meat of the שלמים shlamim and you can eat it
in like all ירושלים, you have a certain amount of control over
it and you're going to benefit from it. So he says קדשים
קלים kodshim kalim is still considered yours. It's not just considered God's
or the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. So therefore if you sanctify an
animal for קדשים קלים kodshim kalim according to רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi
Yosi HaGelili and then it was worshipped—then you worshipped as עבודה זרה,
avodah zarah, you worship it as עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, it makes
it forbidden. It is yours and you can make it forbidden. And
that's the scenario where it was ראוי לאהל מועד, ra'uy l'ohel moed,
but since now it was worshipped, from the extra פסוק pasuk of
לפני משכן השם, lifnei mishkan Hashem, now it's not fit, so you're
not חייב chayav for שחוטי חוץ. shechutei chutz. Okay? דתניא ומעל מעל
בהשם detanya u'maal maal b'Hashem and he did a trespass against God.
That's when somebody swore to deny that he owed something to his
friend. So לרבות קדשים קלים שהן ממונו דברי רבי יוסי הגלילי. lerabot
kodshim kalim shehen mamono divrei Rabbi Yosi HaGelili. So even if you
let's say stole your friend's שלמים shlamim and you took an oath
to deny it, that is you are going to be חייב. chayav.
You're stealing something from him. And he learns it from the פסוק,
בהשם. b'Hashem. Even something that is sanctified, you could still be stealing
it from your friend. This is קדשים קלים kodshim kalim according to
רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yosi HaGelili. So we've got those cases where
it was sanctified and then became forbidden. Sanctified and then act of
bestiality, sanctified but it's קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, then worshipped, and that
was פסוק where it was ראוי לאהל מועד, ra'uy l'ohel moed, so
you needed an extra phrase of לפני משכן lifnei mishkan to exclude
that. But now we have some other ones in the משנה. Mishna.
הילכך, hilkach, says the גמרא, רובע ונרבע דבר ערוה. rovei'a v'nirba devar
ervah. רובע ונרבע rovei'a v'nirba is an act of עריות and it
makes something forbidden even after it's been sanctified. מוקצה ונעבד עבודה כוכבים.
muktzeh v'ne'evad avodah kochavim. מוקצה ונעבד muktzeh v'ne'evad is an עבודה זרה
avodah zarah in the case of, like we said, קדשים קלים kodshim
kalim according to רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. But now we're going to
deal with the ones we haven't mentioned. אתנן ומחיר כלאים יוצא דופן.
etnan u'mechir kilayim yotzei dofen. The other four were אתנן etnan a
gift for a prostitute, מחיר mechir exchange for a dog, כלאים kilayim
a hybrid, and יוצא דופן yotzei dofen
a Caesarean section. So the גמרא says those,
you
know. So where are you going to get a scenario with them
that they started off as sanctified? And something that was a hybrid,
it was born as a hybrid. Where are you going to get
a scenario that that started off as sanctified? What's going to be
the scenarios here? It doesn't seem like it will work. So the
גמרא says בוולדות קדשים קסבר ולדות קדשים בהווייתן הן קדושים. B'vladot Kodshim
kasavar vladot kodshim behavayatan hein kedoshim. We're talking about the case of
that they were born to a sacrifice and it goes by the
opinion that animals that were born from a sacrifice, you had a
female cow and it gave birth, which you sanctified and then it
gave birth to a calf, that that calf only gets its own
sanctity once it's born, not in its mother's womb. So what does
that mean? It means you had this uber, this fetus in the
mother's womb, in this cow's womb, and you sanctified it. So the
fetus was not yet sanctified. It's sort of like its own entity,
but it is not yet קדוש. Kadosh. It's only going to be
קדוש Kadosh when it is born and therefore it is fit for
אוהל מועד, Ohel Moed, but it's not קדוש. Kadosh. It's fit for
אוהל מועד Ohel Moed because it's going to be brought in its
mother's womb, okay, but it's not קדוש. Kadosh. And because it's not
קדוש, Kadosh, then the man like gave this fetus as a gift,
you'd do an exchange with like a handkerchief, obviously you can't access
the fetus, as a gift to a prostitute or exchanged it for
a dog or it happened to be a hybrid, okay, in the
mother's womb. In all those cases, alright, it was both it was
fit for אוהל מועד Ohel Moed even though it had all these
problems because it could get all these problems because it wasn't קדוש.
Kadosh. And it was fit for אוהל מועד Ohel Moed because it
would have been brought because it was in its mother's womb, okay.
And then it gave birth
and by יוצא דופן, Yotze Dofen, well that'll happen anyway when it
gives birth. It's fit to be brought in its mother's womb and
it's only going to be יוצא דופן Yotze Dofen when it gives
birth. And then the animal gives birth and then it becomes קדוש.
Kadosh. So now you have something that was fit for אוהל מועד
Ohel Moed when it was in the mother's womb, even though that's
also where the problems were. And now it's קדוש Kadosh because it
was born. And now you're still going to be exempt for what
do you call it, for שחוטי חוץ Shechutei Chutz because לפני משכן
ה', Lifnei Mishkan Hashem, even though at one point it was fit
for אוהל מועד Ohel Moed in its mother's womb, it now is
no longer fit and therefore you're not חייב Chayav for שחוטי חוץ.
Shechutei Chutz. Okay, we will end with that.